Inventory of the Theodocius Joshua Scurlock Papers 1855-1888
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Letters and Papers, 1860-1869., 38 items. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1860, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:6-7)
    - G.B. McNiel, Phila[delphia] Nes[hoba] County, Miss[issippi] to friend [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [New Orleans, Louisiana ], 29 August 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Sorry to hear [Scurlock's] mother is dissatisfied with her move to Texas, but has heard many are; the drought continues, has traveled to Alabama and 200 miles up Alabama River and found the drought reaches further; friends wanted to look him up in New Orleans; encourages him to come visit; other family and town news.
    - T[homas] H. Harbison, Polk County, Texas to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 4 September 1860., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      All in good health, crops are turning out better than expected; has traded land in Tennessee for land in Texas; reports murder of old man by child in Sumpter [South Carolina], in jail waiting trial; coal is scarce, other family and area news.
    - Dan Scurlock n.p. to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 4 September 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Received letter with thesis, contained information they already had, refers to the lawsuit thesis was needed for; finally received rain which rejuvenated crops; health of area has been good, "too much so for the good of the Doctors", refers to murder committed by Jack Taliaferro, includes other town news.
    - G.B. McNiel, Phila[delphia] Nesh[oba] County Miss[issippi] to friend [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 21 September 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Begs "Dosh" to come and visit him, outlines how to get to Philadelphia; all are well, has heard from Scurlock's mother who hates Texas and wants to return to Alabama.
    - R.A. Brown, Baton Rouge, Louisiana to [Theodocius Joshua] Scurlock, n.p., 9 Sept. [18]60., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Promises to pay what he owes in few weeks.
    - T[homas] H. Harbison, Polk County, Texas to friend T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 10 October 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Corn crop better than expected; relates robbery charges against men from Polk County and other town news.
    - Bailey Barton, Pittsburg, Upshur County, Texas to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 15 October 1860., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Describes details of common friend's death, also refers vaguely to various other [medical] cases "town is improving, have built a female college and have a Methodist preacher who will convert...the negroes and dogs before they stop", other town news.
    - Dan Scurlock, n.p. to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 23 Oct. 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Gives lengthy opinion of upcoming Presidential election between Douglas and Lincoln and also projection and hopes for house and Senate elections; other family news.
    - Dan Scurlock Mt. Pleasant [Texas] to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 27 Nov. 1860., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      "Bad crops, low water and high prices"; will be traveling back to Polk County before Christmas; gives results of Presidential elections; other family news.
    - W.W., Corrie, Pittsburg, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] S[curlock], n.p., 29 Dec. [1860 ?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      All well; friend has stopped drinking; this friend wants to fight when war begins; [Brother] Dan "fixing n to go see Mother; other news.
  - Letters and Papers, 1862, 2 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Diploma of Medicine for Theodocius Scurlock from Louisiana University [Tulane] (in Latin), 5 March 1862., 1 page. D.S. See medium oversized file. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - T.N. Pitts, Pittsburg, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 6 Sept. 1862., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Hasn't heard from him; corn crops good, leaf worm has injured cotton crops; has decided to study medicine; hopes girlfriend hasn't decided to marry someone else, encourages Scurlock to marry; relates town affairs.
  - M.W. Davis, Livingston, Polk County [Texas] to friend "Dosh" [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 10 Sep[tember] 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Asks advice on collecting lawyers in Upshur County, has not gotten judgement on claims of Scurlock's; Frank Bensen has eloped with Darby's wife; cotton crops poor.
  - Letters, 1867, 14 items. (Box-folder 2:1-2)
    - T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Texas State Lunatic Asylum, Austin, Texas to Wilson L. Collins, n.p., 3 January 1867., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Expresses his opinion about national politics, predicts a military governor for Texas judging by the acts of the "Vandal Congress," has no faith in "Andrew Johnson the chief of drunkards of the Vandal states." Advises to sue, D.J. Kimball for money he owes; has not heard from Pittsburg and will write a "cuss lettr" if they "do not respond".
    - D[an] Scurlock [Mt. Pleasant, Texas], to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., 3 Feb. 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Has had to harvest his own cotton because he has no laborers; hired no freedmen because of some fights the previous year; will give up farming and maybe sell rugs with Dr. Hendricks; money is hard to come by; [Brother] Bill just recovering from serious illness; other family news.
    - T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Austin City, Texas, to brother Dan Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas, 3 March 1867., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Shows very little faith in the "Vandal n government; questions whether Dan has received the horse he sent; business not very good, advises that one should run business on a cash system; relates he has lost about $200 on a credit based system; had had difficulty with superintendent of Lunatic Asylum, told him what he thought of him and challenged him to a fight, all stemmed from disagreement on treatment of patients; will be leaving soon.
    - D[an] Scurlock n.p. to brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock n.p., 7 April 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Will begin selling rugs, have ordered supply from New Orleans; hopes doing better in city than would have at Asylum; other family news.
    - D[an Scurlock] Mt. Pleasant, Texas to AL[?] n.p., 6 June 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Has not heard from brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] since March; would like any information on him as had heard rumor that he had been killed; selling goods with Dr. Hendricks in "six full stores in Mt. Pleasant".
    - D[an] Scurlock n.p. to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 24 June 1867., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Relates rumors that T.J. is dead and how this rumor came about; Long guilt speech about the death of his mother; never received the horse sent to him; other family news.
    - F.C. Swain, Austin, Texas to friend "Sky" [?] n.p., 14 July 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Discusses different medical cases and dental cases; relates deaths of acquaintances; has been very ill.
    - G.B. McNiel Phila[delphia], Nesoba County Miss[issippi] to friend T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock n.p., 2 August 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Mentions Scurlock has left Austin but not where he's gone; war has ruined him; crops have been good; at home at time of surrender; has begun preaching and serving his God.
    - F. Carry C. Swain, Waco, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock n.p., 20 Aug[u]st 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Have been in city 5 days, very different from Austin; many sick town supporting 10-12 Doctors and many drug stores; has met a gay widow with whom he keeps company.
    - C.M. Etheredge [?], Austin, Texas to Dr. [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 4 Sept. 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Enquires of a Claiborne Herbert in Columbus, Colorado County; has opened a school but is doing poorly, would appreciate any help Scurlock could give; gives update on doctors [from Austin Lunatic Asylum]; will be leaving Austin soon.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant [Texas] to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] n.p., 15 September 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Has been in poor health; crops have been very poor; war has destroyed the South and the "Southern devils have a hard hand of it after we get through a war in which we lose everything"; will continue in business if can.
    - Louis C. Wise, Austin [Texas] to Dr. [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] n.p., 17 Sept. 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Jobs hard to get in Austin; Doctors from Lunatic Asylum did not do well in private practice, have gone to Georgetown; negro notary has been appointed in Austin, other town news.
    - Harry C.Swain, Waco, Texas, to friend "Sky" [?] n.p., 21 Sept. 1867., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Did not make as much in business here as in Bastrop; encourages Sky to join him and "Dock" in Austin; Dock will pay his passage to Austin; 2 deaths from yellow fever; enjoying company of "The widow".
    - Harry Swain, Austin, Texas, to friend "Sky," n.p., 13 Oct. 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Austin dull place; Gen. [Joseph Jones] Reynolds has arrived to take over department; Boon has located office, not doing well; City covered with grasshoppers; describes as "damb poor country"; "Better be in Hell without claws".
  - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], Mexico, 10 Oct. 1869., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Describes his plans to get in touch with brother; feels government is in bad condition, "Texas will soon pass through to fiery ordeal of what is denominated reconstruction.", expresses his prejudices toward Blacks; begs brother to come back to Texas.
  Series 3: Letters, 1870-1879
- Letters, 1870-1879., 6 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Letters, 1870, 4 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - W.L. Collins, Jefferson, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tuxpan, Mexico, 24 Feb. 1870., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Expresses opinion of government: "I hope it [government] will sink to the latter most pits of Hell."; has been able to collect some relates town news.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant Texas to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] n.p., 25 May 1870., 7 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Waited until Texas was accepted back into the Union; considers this a good gained from reconstruction; claims Negroes will remain in place they should, inferior position; wants to know about Mexico: politics, commercial facilities and social events; encourages him to come back to the U.S.; other town news.
    - W.L. Collins, Jefferson, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tuxpan Republic of Mexico, 25 June 1870., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Relates local political happenings through reconstruction; and some very strong opinions; thanks for the description of Mexico; sends regards of many people and relates other family and town news.
    - W.L. Collins, Jefferson, Texas to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tuxpan "Republick" of Mexico, 6 Aug. 1870., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Relates his preconception of Mexico; "hopes to see all Democrats elected" in upcoming elections; other town news.
  - T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tamiahua, Tuxpan, Republic of Mexico to brother [Dan Scurlock] n.p., 18 Ja[nuar]y 1871., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Does not agree that Democrats have never changed, has been in poor health; is doing well in profession; explains his problems at the Asylum; eating in Mexico is cheap; is studying man; [contains several passages with no meaning].
  - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant Texas, to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] [Fantima, State of Vera Cruz, Mexico], 25 May 1879., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Hasn't heard from him in 2 months; encourages him to come visit Mt. Pleasant; claims it will be one of the most important small towns when the railroad is built from St. Louis through Texarkana; is now assessing taxes for the county; other family news; includes envelope.
  Series 4: Letters, 1880-1889
- Letters, 1880-1889., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:3-4)
  - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas to brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock], n.p., 3 March 1882., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Wife not well with ovarian tumor; has become partner in goods firm; still county tax assessor; receives 6500 for this job; Mt. Pleasant included on Railroad which begins in St. Louis and will go to the Rio Grande to connect with Mexican rail encourages him to come and visit.
  - T.J. Eckards and J. Tessier, Tuscpan [Mexico] to Mr. Teodocio [Theodocius] J. Scurlock, Fantima, Mexico, 20 August 1883., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Received account against Jose Gamundi for $73.88; has placed credit in his name for $73.88.
  - Letters, 1884, 2 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - A.M. Boyd, Tuxpan [Mexico] to T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, M.D., Fantima, Mexico, 26 June 1884., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Refers to securing claims on oil wells and coal mines; expects that there will be a boom in oil lands after [Mexican] Presidential election; hopes to do some speculating; hopes to settle himself financially for life.
    - A.M. Boyd Tuxpan, [Mexico] to Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Fantima [Mexico], 5 Nov. 1884., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Sickness is increasing; has received "Charge of the Vice-consulate property." refers to a matter concerning archives [records of the consulate?], other town news.
  - Letters, 1886, 5 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - D[an] Scurlock Mt. Pleasant, Texas to brother Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock [Fantina, Mexico], 22 Janu[uar]y 1886., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Is now working at a bank as a cashier and continues to assess taxes; is living comfortably but still must pay off some debts from Merchandising; family is well and being educated as he would like; refers to the Democratic Victory for Presidency and remarks "that the south is again at the Head of National affairs;" other family news.
    - Mary D. Pitts, Milledgeville, Georgia to cousin T[heodocius] Josh[ua] Scurlock, [Mexico], 14 March 1886., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Introduces herself by reminding him of when she was a child; makes a plea for money which she needs; begs him not to pass judgement on her for asking for money.
    - Claude Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas to his uncle Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tamiahua; Mexico, 28 March 1886., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Gives description of himself: gives family news; describes Mt. Pleasant; asks many questions about Mexico and whether a Doctor could do well there; hopes to study medicine.
    - Claude Scurlock Mt. Pleasant, Texas to Uncle Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, [Mexico], 18 May 1886., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Gives town news; crops look good, had a hail storm nearby; has chosen medicine as a prospective occupation; town working hard to raise money for railroad to town; includes lineage of Scurlock family.
    - J. Tessier, Tuscpan [Mexico] to Mr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tamiaqua [Mexico], 23 October 1886., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Acknowledges "carta"[?] and list of goods sent to him; will do all in his power as executor of his will to deliver property safely.
  - Mary M. Harris Mt. Pleasant, Texas to Uncle Dr. T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tamiahua, Mexico, 24 Jan. 1887., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
    Questions why he hasn't come to visit; gives description of herself; relates father's [Dan Scurlock] poor health; gives some town news.
  - Letters, 1888, 6 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - William L. Scurlock, Carrigan, Polk County, Texas to J. Tessier, Tuscpan, Mexico, 16 April 1888., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Questions will of Dr. Theodocius [Joshua] Scurlock; inquires whether estate was left to brothers individually and was it lawful under Mexican laws; others are trying to come in on will.
    - J.Tessier, Tusc[pan, Mexico] to William J. Scurlock, Corrigan [Polk County] Texas, 5 May 1888., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Not acquainted with Mexican laws but believes the brother [William and Dan] are only benefactors.
    - J. Tessier, Tuscpan [Mexico] to Daniel Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas, 14 May 1888., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Remits trunks and a box containing possession of brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock]; has sold amputating instruments for $20 to local hospital; will send due cash as soon a possible.
    - J. Tessier, Tuscpan [Mexico] to Daniel Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Texas, 7 June 1888., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Assures him possessions have been sent; explains that his brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] did not have a great estate when he died; advises him to contact two friends who knew him; requests a receipt sent to him from [Scurlock's] papers.
    - D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant, Titus County Texas to A. G. Pardue, Agt., Southern Express Co. [New Orleans, Louisiana ], 9 June 1888., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Inquiring about possessions of deceased brother [Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] which he has not yet received; requests that he make some enquires; refers to his brother's assassination.
    - C.A. Pardue, agt. New Orleans, Louisiana to D[an] Scurlock, Mt. Pleasant Texas, 12 June 1888., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Informs him goods have arrived, will pay duties and willship as soon as possible.
  Series 5: Letters, no date
- Letters, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, Tuxpan [Mexico] to [brother Dan Scurlock ?] [Mt. Pleasant Texas], n.d., 6 pages, pages 1 and 2 missing. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Discusses the advantages of living outside of the U.S.; shows his bitterness toward U.S. politics, racial problems and how the government is taking care of them; defends Mexico as a better place to live; discourages any immigration.
    Pages 1 and 2 missing.
  - L[ucena] Scurlock [Macon County, Alabama] to [son Theodocius Joshua Scurlock] n.p., n.d., fragment. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Relates Bill Moore's crime of forgery for 50 bales of cotton and his arrest.
  - Mary P. Darby, n.p. to her brother T[heodocius] J[oshua] Scurlock, n.p., n.d., fragment. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Begs brother to return to Marshall to comfort Mother and rest of family; relates [sister] 'Mit' has married; also "Beany [?]" was shot dead previous morning.
  Series 6: Diary
- Diary of Theodocius Joshua Scurlock containing details of Dr. Scurlock's journey from Texas to Tulango, Mexico, December 1867 - April 1869., 162 pages. MsV. with TCy. (Box-folder 2:6)
  Diary of Theodocius Joshua Scurlock containing details of Dr. Scurlock's journey from Texas to Tulango, Mexico; his impressions of the lifestyles of the people he encountered as he traveled south and the novelties he sees and learns about for the first time; and a table of distances traveled, detailed weather reports, and descriptions of the locations and names of towns stayed in. It gives an insight to the questioning nature of Dr. Scurlock and his ability to describe some of the methods of technique he viewed (e.g., medical and spinning). It also contains lists of edible birds and animals, trees for lumber and various fruit trees and vegetables.